Chester E. Gillette Collection
Chester E. Gillette Collection
1905-1939
Gillette, Chester.
0.3 linear ft.
Materials relating to the trial and execution of Chester Gillette for the murder of Grace Brown in 1905, including photocopies of correspondence, autopsy reports, court records, hotel records, a judgement of the appeal to the Supreme Court, judges remarks, a prison statement about Gillette's execution, trial description, list of witnesses, love letters of Gillette and Grace Brown, newspapers clippings, and a telegram to Judge Ward. This case served as the basis of Theodore Dreiser's novel, American tragedy.
149002
Scope and Contents of the Collection
All the materials in this collection are xerox copies of the original. The originals are located at Hamilton College Library.
The Chester E. Gillette Collection includes incoming and outgoing correspondence, autopsy reports, court records, hotel records, a judgement of the appeal to the Supreme Court, judge's remarks, a prison statement about Gillette's execution, unidentified material, a statement of Gillette, a description of the trial, a laundry statement, a list of the official witnesses, love letters from the decedent, newspaper clippings and comments about the trial and a telegram.
Correspondence contains incoming correspondence arranged alphabetically by author and outgoing correspondence arranged alphabetically by the person to whom it was sent. Where possible these materials are further arranged chronologically. Dates: 1905, 1906, 1939 and undated. 8 Folders
Subject file contains autopsy reports, court reports, a description of the trial, court reports, a laundry statement, a judgement of the appeal to the Supreme Court, the judge's remarks at the trial, a prison statement of the execution and unidentified material. This material is arranged by subject. Dates: 1906, 1908 and undated. 10 Folders
Manuscripts includes a statement by Gillette concerning the trial and his innocence. Dates: undated. 1 Folder
Published material consists of a list of the official witnesses at the trial, the published love letters of the decedent Grace Brown to Gillette, newspaper clippings and comments on the trial and a telegram. These materials are arranged alphabetically by type. Dates: 1906, 1908, 1938. 7 Folders
Subject and Genre Headings
New York State; Gillette, Chester.; Brown, Grace, 1885 or 1886-1906.; Murder, New York (State); Trials (Murder) -- New York (State); Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Judicial records.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Incoming
    - Grace Brown, 1906 and; undated (Box 1)
    - L.M. Gillette, Mrs., 1906 (Box 1)
  - Outgoing
    - Grace Brown, 1905-1906 (Box 1)
    - Grace Brown, 1905-1906 (Box 1)
    - L.M. Gillette, Mrs., 1906 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence of others
    - To W.A. Breckwoldt from Daniel Pananicles, 1939 (Box 1)
    - To Grace Brown from Maude Crund, 1906 (Box 1)
    - To Judge Ward from Albert M. Mills, 1906 (Box 1)
    - Telegram: Note to Judge Ward, 1906 (Box 1)
- Subject file
  - Autopsy reports, 1906 (Box 1)
  - Court records, 1906 (Box 1)
  - Description of trial, 1906 (Box 1)
  - Hotel records
    - Hotel Glenmore, July 4- July 8, 1906 (Box 1)
    - Hotel Martin, July 9 and; undated, 1906 (Box 1)
    - Raymond House, July 4, 1906 (Box 1)
    - Taber House, July 6- July 9, 1906 (Box 1)
  - Judgement of appeal, 1906 (Box 1)
  - Judge's remarks, 1906 (Box 1)
  - Laundry statement, 1906 (Box 1)
  - Prison statement of execution, 1908 (Box 1)
  - Unidentified, undated (Box 1)
- Manuscripts
  - Statement by Gillette, undated (Box 1)
- Published material
  - List of official witnesses, 1906 (Box 1)
  - Love letters, 1906 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper comments
    - 1938 (Box 1)
    - Annotated copy of Brown's love letters pamphlets by George Ward, 1906 (Box 1)